Guide to the New-York Historical Society Collection of Scrapbooks and Clippings, 1709-1974 MS 3158
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society collection of scrapbooks and clippings
1709-1974
New-York Historical Society
MS 3158
100 Linear feet (approximately) in 67 boxes
The collection consists of approximately 200 volumes of scrapbooks acquired from various sources over the course of New-York Historical's history. The collection was formed in 2019-22 as an administrative convenience for the inventorying and description of a miscellany of previously uncataloged scrapbooks. Clippings from newspapers and other sources perhaps predominate the collection, but there are many other document forms as well, including photographs, some letters, programs, tickets, and other ephemera. The scrapbooks in this collection range from those that have a focus on an individual's social, leisure or work/career life to those that document, mostly through clippings, various historical or other matters of apparent interest to the scrapbook's compiler, such as the Civil War, politics, boxing, and more.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to consult it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Accruals
It is possible, though unlikely, that N-YHS will add new accessions to this collection. The more likely possibility is that over time additional uncataloged scrapbooks might be found and those could be added to this collection.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was formed in 2019-22 by New-York Historical Society to encompass various uncataloged individual scrapbooks or small multi-volume sets of scrapbooks. The scrapbooks comprising the collection are from various sources, not all of which could be readily determined when the finding aid was prepared. Acquisition information that could be readily determined, often from a bookplate in the album or tracing a date noted in the album to the accession ledgers, was noted at the scrapbook entry below.
Arrangement
The container list is arranged in rough chronological order, based on the earliest known date in the album's range. Many items in the albums are undated and the contents were determined based on skims by the archivist so the date ranges should be considered to be rough approximations. The albums are of various sizes and are boxed accordingly.
Administrative History
New-York Historical Society initiated the scrapbook and clippings collection in 2019 as a means of establishing a baseline inventory for the many uncataloged scrapbooks it held at that time. Over the course of its history, N-YHS collected scrapbooks either as standalone items (that is, as a single scrapbook or as a multi-volume set of scrapbooks) or as part of a larger acquisition of personal papers or other documents. Cataloging practices for scrapbooks generally or for particular scrapbooks varied over the institution's history. Consequently, as of 2019, the status of scrapbooks in relation to cataloging could generally be categorized as: included in the catalog record of a larger collection of personal or institutional papers; cataloged as a standalone item; or not cataloged at all.
Beginning in 2019, in connection with the clearance of the library stacks in preparation for a major expansion/construction project, N-YHS's shelves of scrapbooks were cleared, with any uncataloged/uninventoried scrapbooks receiving some baseline descriptive treatment. Scrapbooks determined to have been separated at some point from a larger collection were reconnected and cataloged with that collection. Others, especially large multi-volume sets of scrapbooks, received standalone catalog records. Most single volume or small multi-volume sets, often unknown as to compiler and/or donor, were inventoried in this collection's finding aid, and cataloged as a whole.
For purposes of compiling this collection, "scrapbooks" was defined somewhat broadly. It includes albums of mixed media (ephemera, programs, cards, letters, clippings, photographs, etc.) and albums in which one media type predominates, or is found exclusively, such as with newspaper clippings. It also includes packets or boxes of documents, such as newspaper clippings, that are scrapbook-like in their nature, though not housed in an album. This was simply based on the practical consideration of getting a baseline inventory for such uncataloged material before it was moved to offsite storage.
Related Materials
N-YHS has processed and cataloged scrapbooks in various ways over time and will continue to do so, depending on both internal and professional practices, curatorial choices, the context of particular scrapbooks, etc. For example, many scrapbooks have been cataloged individually. Others were categorized differently and placed in other collections, such as the Album Collection (PR 2). And others remain associated with their provenance and context in larger bodies of individual, family, or organizational papers. To identify scrapbooks across N-YHS's collections, search on the keyword "scrapbooks" in N-YHS's on-line catalog, Bobcat, and in the discovery portal for full-text search of all finding aids.
Scope and Contents
The collection holds about 100 single-volume scrapbooks, multi-volume sets of scrapbooks, or compilations of clippings not necessarily bound in an album, totalling almost 200 volumes. Newspaper clippings, often deteriorating, likely make up most of the content of the collection and are commonly the exclusive content of many of the scrapbooks. Nevertheless, various other types of documents can be found throughout, especially programs (theatre, concerts, other events) and ephemera (tickets, cards, invitations, event announcements, brochures, etc.). There are some photographs but these are not found extensively; more common are pictorial works, such as postcards and those clipped from newspapers and elsewhere. There are also some letters, though not extensive.
There is a considerable degree of diversity in subject content. The container list attempts to identify the fundamental subject matter or focus of the inventoried scrapbooks and the principal document types in each. Very few of the scrapbooks were titled and so a working title/label for each could be determined by the processing archivist based only on skims within time constraints and so cannot necessarily be fully relied on. Where an album was explicitly titled, that is shown within "quotation marks" in the container list. All other titles/labels were established by the archivist. Generally that title/label used the scrapbook compiler if known, or the subject focus as best as could be perceived.
Following is an attempt to categorize the scope of the scrapbooks:
Several scrapbooks document aspects of an individual's life and/or career, and were compiled by that person. While clippings provide some context, there are typically other and more personal documentary forms in these scrapbooks. Examples of these include:
• William Alfred Robbins scrapbooks, one of which documents his work as overseas secretary for the YMCA War Work during and in the aftermath of World War I.
• Lawrence-Smith School for Boys scrapbook, compiled by its headmaster and tracing the school's history from beginning (1914) to dissolution (1939).
• Edmond Charles Bonaventure scrapbooks, which document his involvement with the French Institute in the United States, circa 1914.
• Dea Carroll scrapbook, which documents the singer/entertainer's career as charity fashion show host, 1953-61.
• Helen Sargent Hitchcock scrapbook concerning the Art War Relief auxiliary of the Red Cross during WWI.
• Charles B. Curtis scrapbook documenting his travels across the United States, Europe, and Asia in 1905-06.
• Programs of musical performances that included the tenor Frederick Specht, 1875-89.
• Alan R. Hawley scrapbooks on "aeronautics," that is, ballooning and early airplane flight, both of which he was an active participant in, 1906-37.
• George Ehler Stonebridge scrapbooks concerning his career as a photographer, poet, and lecturer, 1890s-1930s.
Several scrapbooks include documents that reflect social connections or leisure activities. Examples of these include:
• Marguerite Adelaide Wolfe scrapbook of dances and other social engagements in Narragansett, 1877-78.
• Sydney H. Carney, Jr. scrapbooks of meeting announcements and the like from the Society of Colonial Wars in the State of New York, Society of the Sons of the Revolution in the State of New York, New-York Historical Society, and other organizations he was a member and officer of.
• Laura Valentine Sawyer scrapbook, documenting her high school years as a Brooklyn teenager, 1912-16.
Several scrapbooks hold collections of certain document types, such as trade cards and other advertising material, calling cards, monograms, prints of artworks or other illustrations, etc. Theater and other programs are found in several scrapbooks, including those of William K. Draper, Betsey (Bessie) van Nostrand Smith, Faye Laird, and others.
Newspaper clippings perhaps predominate the collection. While many of these scrapbooks seem to be compilations of miscellaneous articles of interest to the (often unknown) compiler, many scrapbooks of clippings have a perceptible focus. Examples of these include:
• J.B. Stack's scrapbooks on boxing around the turn of the 20th century.
• Henry E. Davies and Julia Stevens scrapbooks on the 1876 United States centennial celebrations.
• Lispenard Stewart's seven volumes of clippings about himself and his political and social activities.
• Several scrapbooks include clippings about the Civil War.
• An unattributed volume concerning bicycles and bicycling, 1897-98.
• 7 volumes of newspaper articles and images principally concerning naval military matters, especially in connection with the U.S. Navy, 1898-1912.
• Charles W. Bryan scrapbook on the 1940 presidential election.
Clippings of speeches, poems, anecdotes, and other literary pieces are found in many of the scrapbooks. Examples include:
• Richard Wood scrapbook, circa 1800
• Catherine Kimball scrapbook, circa 1836
• Alburn Hager Krum scrapbook, circa 1860s-90s
• A highly structured and indexed scrapbook with clippings from 1841-45 with speeches on various national topics.
New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; New York (N.Y.) -- History.; United States -- Anniversaries, etc.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865.; Depictions (visual works); Newspaper clippings.; Photographs.; Poems; Printed ephemera.; Programs (documents); Scrapbooks.; Ballooning.; Boxing -- United States.; Children -- United States.; Elections -- United States.; Performing arts.; Speeches, addresses, etc.; Veterans -- New York (State); Women -- United States.; World War, 1914-1918.
- Howland Pell scrapbook, 1709-1927 (Offsite-box 18)
  Scope and Contents
  1 volume compiled by Howland Pell that primarily holds bound issues of Harper's Weekly and Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper from various dates ranging from 1857-1927. In addition there are several other newspapers folded loosely into the album. These papers range from 1709 (The Tattler, #144) to 1836, and include the Sun, New York Gazette, Gazette of the United States, and others. Noted particularly by Pell in an inscription is an issue of the Columbian Courier of 1804 with the wording of a note written by Alexander Hamilton concerning his impending duel with Aaron Burr. Source: Gift, January 7, 1936.
- "Anchors", 1783? (Offsite-box 54)
  One volume with plates 1-9 concerning anchors (ancres in the original French) from Benard Firexit's "Encyclopédie Méthodique" (available in Google Books). Source: Gift? of Louis S. Tiemann.
- 19th century clippings scrapbook, 1788-1831 (Offsite-box 27)
  1 volume of clippings. There is a table of contents at the front of the volume. It begins with clippings about the ratification of the U.S. Constitution in 1788. The bulk of the clippings date from about 1828 and are of speeches, orations, etc.
- Richard Wood scrapbook, circa 1800 (Offsite-box 1)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings containing poetry and various other pieces of literature.
- "Documents relating to the purchase of Louisiana & Georgia claims", 1800-1806 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 volume of clippings compiled from newspapers on the above topics. Clippings are both glued into the volume and lie loose in it. The inside back cover includes a list from the Daily Advertiser of deaths in New York from yellow fever from July 19 to October 19, 1803. Source: Gift of Joseph Sands, January 23, 1817.
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks re: New York history (Box 1 of 3), circa 1829-1935 (Offsite-box 50)
  4 volumes, primarily of clippings, concerning the history of New York City from colonial days to the 1930s, though especially 19th century and earlier. The emphasis generally seems to be on buildings, events, and prominent people. It is not known if Stack compiled the volumes, or collected them as is. This first album (in Box 50) is a palimpsest volume, formerly holding invoices of the 1890s which were largely removed, with clippings ranging from the 1880s to the 1920s, and mostly concern the subjects of women in the city, the 1896 police "Sherry raid" involving the dancer "Little Egypt," the sinking of the Lusitania and the Titanic, and the General Slocum explosion. The second volume (in Box 64) ranges from roughly 1829 to 1929 and has ephemera and pictorial works as well as clippings. The third and fourth volumes (in Boxes 64 and 65) are entirely clips and are very unstructured with most of the content consisting of loose items; they range from the mid 1800s into the 1920s and 1930s also. Source: Gift of J.B. Stack, November 4, 1953. (See also below circa 1890 for Stack's scrapbooks on boxing.)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks re: New York history (Box 2 of 3), circa 1829-1935 (Offsite-box 64)
- J.B. Stack scrapbooks re: New York history (Box 3 of 3), circa 1829-1935 (Offsite-box 65)
- Clarkson Maverick scrapbook, 1830-1890s (Offsite-box 58)
  1 volume compiled by Clarkson Maverick (fuller name was William K.C. Maverick), an actor primarily of comedic roles often, judging from some documents in the album, based on Irish characters, masquerades, and minstrelsy. Maverick's inscription at the front of the album says it is "a book for miscellaneous matter, scraps, &c." and is dated April of 1860. Much of the early pages of the album relate to theatre, to Maverick, and to his wife, Persis (Jones). They married in 1874 and she died in 1895. Documents include concert programs, some of which included Maverick (e.g. performances of the Jolly Comedians in Hoboken, N.J.); writings by Maverick; Red Star Line and Inman Line steamship passenger lists; and birthday and holiday greetings. Related clippings are mixed in, most notably for an 1896 event in Windham, N.Y. at which Maverick appeared dressed as a woman and in blackface to recite Lucy Stone Blackwell's lecture on women's rights. Much of the album, though, consists of miscellaneous clippings, related to the Civil War (1860s), Tammany Hall (1880s-90s), literary pieces, anecdotes, and other matter. Some original documents (one dating to 1830) refer to Samuel Maverick, possibly Clarkson's father. Source: Purchase with the Wilbur Fund, February 1945.
- "Laws and ordinances relating to the Baltimore and Susquehanna Rail Road Company", 1831-circa 1845 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 published volume of "Laws and ordinances relating to the Baltimore and Susquehanna Rail Road Company" (1831), with additional related clippings and handwritten notes to circa 1845 inserted. The compiler was likely one Charles Howard of Baltimore, whose name appears on the cover. Source: Gift of Daniel Parish, Jr., February 17, 1890.
- Isaac F. Wood scrapbook, circa 1832-1865 (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of invitations, clippings, and ephemera about the celebrations of George Washington's birthday. Source: Gift of Isaac Wood, 1895.
- Catherine Kimball scrapbook, circa 1836, 1856 (Offsite-box 25)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings of poems. Pasted on the front endpaper is a small clip that appears to be from a bookseller's catalog and that seems to describe the volume: "Contains several early poems of Hannah F. Gould, N.P. Willis, J.G. Whittier (including "The Spectre Ship of Salem," never included in his writings), Salem broadsides, carriers' addresses, etc." There are many other authors represented in the scrapbook than are noted in that description. One outlier in the contents is an 1856 facsimile of a 1723 issue of the New-England Courant.
- Catherine G. Fraser's children's scrapbook, circa 1840s (Offsite-box 63)
  One volume compiled by Catherine G. Fraser (Mrs. Robert Mackie) for her children. The Fraser family lived in England until 1849 when they immigrated to America. The volume includes colored illustrations, principally of a caricature and cartoon nature, with poems and short stories or other narrative content. There is a contextual note provided by the donor at the front of the album. Source: Gift of Catherine R.B. Mackie, granddaughter of the compiler, July 3, 1947.
- Political clippings scrapbook, 1840s-1886 (Offsite-box 35)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings concerning politics and political figures in New York and nationally. There is some ephemera related to the Tammany Society, also known as the Columbian Order.
- Mrs. Jacob H. Vanderbilt scrapbook, 1840s-1893 (Offsite-box 13)
  1 volume primarily of newspaper clippings from the 1850s-1860s of poetry, historical items, Civil War events, and miscellaneous items concerning women. There are some handwritten poems (circa 1840s) and other notes, some sketches, and a typescript account of the 1893 funeral services for Jacob H. Vanderbilt. Source: Gift of Sybil C. Shugg, December 23, 1953.
- Dolley Madison Jacques scrapbook, 1840-1900 (Offsite-box 1)
  1 volume of letterheads and stationery from various hotels.
- 1840s clippings scrapbook, 1841-1845 (Offsite-box 36)
  2 volumes of clippings by an unknown compiler intended to document the important national issues and remarks of the period 1841-45 in a highly structured manner. The first volume has an introductory contextual note about the content, and both volumes have an index to their respective content. Subject headings of the clippings as noted in the indexes include anniversary dinners, fairs, and religious events, including anti-slavery; lectures, orations, addresses, and speeches (identifying subject and author, with special emphasis on those of Daniel Webster and John Quincy Adams); Irish Repeal; temperance; slavery; capital punishment; and historical reminiscences.
- Isaac Michael Dyckman scrapbook, 1841-1865 (Offsite-box 13)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings regarding political races and national events related to the issues leading to and during the Civil War. Source: Bequest of Fannie Fredericka Welch, September 26, 1951.
- New York State Agricultural Society clippings, 1844, 1850s (Offsite-box 54)
  1 volume that primarily holds clippings from 1844 concerning the New York State Agricultural Society. There are also loose clips on various topics related to steamships, animals, etc. and one manuscript note concerning steam navigation. The compiler of the scrapbook is unknown.
- "Letters from Sabine, Cooper, Van Schaack, and Onderdonck which appeared in the 'Home Journal' concerning some statements made by Mr. Sabine in his 'Loyalists.'", 1848 (Offsite-box 54)
  One slender volume that includes the exchange from the "Home Journal" newspaper (New York) between James Fenimore Cooper, Lorenzo Sabine, Henry Onderdonk, Jr., H.C. Van Schaack, and Vindex concerning Sabine's "American Loyalists." The volume opens with a manuscript of Cooper's February 12, 1848, letter to the editor (it is not clear whether this is a transcription or a draft, or by whose hand, though it is signed with Cooper's name), followed by clips from the newspaper of the resulting responses. With pencil and ink annotations, some initialed "D."
- Henry E. Davies scrapbook, 1849, 1876 (Offsite-box 25)
  1 palimpsest volume. Underlying book is the published "Proceedings of the Board of Aldermen" from 1849. Some pages of the original text are still fully visible. Henry Davies's name and the 1849 date are inscribed in the volume, but it is not known if he was the compiler of the clippings pasted into it. The clips date from 1876 and primarily relate to the celebrations of the centennial of American independence, with additional subjects concerning that year's reunion of the Army of the Potomac and the unveiling of the Horace Greeley bust at Greenwood Cemetery. Many or most of the clippings seem to be from the New York Daily Tribune.
- Dimock family scrapbook and clippings, circa 1850-1905 (Offsite-box 65)
  One volume, mostly with loose clippings. A note indicates that these were formerly in the Dimock Bible. The clips are generally poems or religious-themed, though there are other subjects as well, but no perceptible focus. There are two manuscript notes, including a poem dated 1884.
- Theo McNamee scrapbook, circa 1851 (Offsite-box 5)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings on merchant firm Bowen and McNamee, as well as many anti-slavery clippings.
- "Carl's Tour in Main Street" [Worcester, Massachusetts], 1855 (Offsite-box 54)
  1 volume of clippings of the series "Carl's Tour in Main Street" "Re-published by request, from the Palladium of 1855." The compiler of the clippings is unknown.
- Poetry and other writings scrapbook, circa 1858-1860s (Offsite-box 26)
  1 volume of clippings, primarily of poetry, anecdotes, and lengthy literary pieces. Several pages at the start of the volume center on poetry concerning the Civil War and related events, such as Lincoln's assassination.
- Alburn Hager Krum scrapbook, circa 1860s-1890s (Offsite-box 24)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings of poems, literary items, anecdotes, and various items of interest (e.g., of the transport and installation of the "Cleopatra's Needle" obelisk in Central Park). Source: Gift of Krum's daughter, Gracie B. Krum, March 1, 1951.
- George Agnew scrapbooks, 1860-1912 (Offsite-box 25)
  2 volumes of newspaper clippings. One volume includes clippings concerning various national events from 1886-87. The second volume holds a few Civil War era (1860-62) clips, and some miscellaneous loose clippings from circa 1904-12. Source: Gift of George B. Agnew, May 3, 1929
- Civil War newspaper clippings scrapbook, 1864 (Offsite-box 2)
  1 volume of newspaper clippings regarding battles, developments, and other news on the Civil War.
- "Little Old New York", 1865-1927 (Offsite-box 7)
  1 volume. The spine includes the sub-title "Greenwich Village, etc." Heavily pictorial in content, which is clippings from newspapers, journals, magazines, etc. Subject matter is of important or notable events especially of, but not only, local New York, such as the destruction of historic buildings, troops going off to World War I, etc. Compiled by Philip Corell. Source: Gift of Louise P. Corell, April 21, 1938.
- "Monograms", 1866 (Offsite-box 63)
  One volume of monograms presented as a Christmas gift to W. Rhinelander Stewart by his sister, Louisa S. Trevor. A few are identified and are mostly family/individual names (e.g. Belknap, Bufford, various Astors, Gallatin, etc.).
- Marion Sharclass scrapbook, 1867 (Offsite-box 34)
  1 volume containing art prints, engravings, and illustrations, with some original drawings and photographs. The inside upper cover is dedicated "To Marion Sharclass from her father, 1867." Several of the prints are annotated with the year 1851 and some earlier. The bulk of the prints are from Europe and Turkey and some annotations suggest that perhaps the father collected these while traveling abroad.
- Various pictorial works, 1870s? (Offsite-box 63)